Register of the Bruce Hadley Billings papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Bruce Hadley Billings papers
1944-2004
82086
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
The collection contains maps, photographs, illustrations, correspondence, reports, proceedings, news clippings, and printed matter relating to the role of technology in programs and projects associated with Taiwanese economic development, agriculture, optics, marine science, the selection of computer technology and industrial equipment, as well as materials on aerial mapping for forestry, highways, and the Taiwan Taoyuan International Airport.
Billings, Bruce Hadley, 1915
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American physicist Bruce Hadley Billings earned his PhD at Johns Hopkins University in 1943.
Billings later served as the American Commissioner of the Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction (JCRR) in China and concurrently served as the Special Assistant for Science and Technology to the United States Ambassador to the Republic of China (Taiwan) from 1968 to 1973.
In 1970, Billings worked with Bell Telephone Laboratories (Bell Laboratories) and made observations about building telephone components and electronic systems, thus having an impact on trade between Taiwan and the United States and aiding in Taiwan's economic growth. In 1972, Billings was decorated with the Order of Brilliant Stara civilian order from Taiwan for outstanding contributions to the development of its nation given to both domestic and foreign nationals.
In the 1980s, Billings served as director of optical companies such as Bell and Howell LLC., and Taiwan Electro-optical Systems. Billings was assigned five United States patents, including one for an improved bolometer that he co-invented with Walter Hyde and Edgar Barr.
Source:
Bruce Hadley Billings papers, Hoover Institution Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains maps, photographs, illustrations, correspondence, reports, proceedings, news clippings, and printed matter relating to the role of technology in programs and projects associated with Taiwanese economic development, agriculture, optics, marine science, the selection of computer technology and industrial equipment, as well as materials on aerial mapping for forestry, highways, and the Taiwan Taoyuan International Airport.
Correspondence files include reports on Billings' visits to institutions in the Republic of China (Taiwan). Reports cover proceedings and conferences in joint effort with the government of the United States as well as independent reports and findings from agencies within the Republic of China. Writings cover the programs that Billings spearheaded in Taiwan.
Arrangement Statement
Files are named and arranged according to the original order imposed by the creator.
Agriculture--Taiwan.; Taiwan--Economic conditions.; Technology--Taiwan.
- Correspondence, 1966-2004
  - Aerospace, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1973 February-March (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1973 March-April (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1973 May (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1973 June (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - 1973 July (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - 1973 August (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - 1973 September (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - 1973 October (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Billings' Taiwan trip, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Billings' visit to National Taiwan War College, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Chungshan Research Institute Material Science United States Air Force, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Dr. K. T. Li, 1988 January-June (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes March 1988 biography of Dr. K. T. (Kwoh-Ting) Li.
  - Platt, Joseph, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Platt, Joseph--Yang,Tsui-hua, 1998-2004 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    Correspondence primarily between Joseph Platt, Alison Allstate, and Robert H. Sheeks.
  - Seitz, Frederick, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Reports File, 1957-1989
  - Aerial Photography in Taiwan and Hawkins L. Slattum proposal, 1970 February-September (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Includes map of Taiwan entitled, "New Programs Requiring Aerial Photography and Photogrammetry 1970-1971 for Planning and Regional Development."
  - Comments and reports, 1957-1973 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Commission on International Relations, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Computer program in Taiwan and Ruth Davis proposal, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Edward David's visit to Taiwan, 1972 April-June (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Frankel's report on Graduate Studies in Taiwan, 1970 July-August (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - National Academy of Science (NAS) Academia Sinica Seminar, 1975 June-August (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Patent project, 1958-1975 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Patent system, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Joseph Platt files, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - "Report on Graduate Centers in Engineering and Science, Republic of China,", 1971 May (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - ROC-STAG (Republic of China, Science and Technology Advisory Group) reports and conference materials, 1984-1989
    Organization is also known as Science and Technology Advisory Group to the Executive Yuan, Republic of China and ROC STAG.
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1986 Interim Consultative Conference, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - 1987 conference files, 1987 August-December (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - ROC-USA (Republic of China-United States of America) material, 1980-1983
    - Workshop on Renewable Energy proceedings, 1982 May (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Colloquium on Marine Science, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Industrial Energy Conservation proceedings, 1980 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Workshop on Food Safety in ROC proceedings, 1981 February (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Sino-American materials, 1968-1975
    - Cooperative Mapping and Map Exchange Agreement, 1972 January (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Colloquium on Ocean Resources, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Workshop on Industrial Innovation and Product Development, 1975 April (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Workshop on Scientific and Technology Information, 1974 February - 1974 July (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction Computer Program (JCRRC) prepared by Edward Floyd Pope, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
- Subject File, 1947-1975
  - Oceanography program on research vessel Chiu-Lien, 1947-1975 (Box-folder 5: 3-4)
    Includes proposals, news clippings, correspondence, and reports on oceanography and the RV Chiu Lien.
  - Institute of Oceanography, National Taiwan University, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Includes correspondence, reports, reference materials and tables on the purchase of industrial products and machinery.
- Writings, 1960-1982
  - "Science and Technology Advisory Group Meeting," draft transcription, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Meeting minutes and reports covering Hepatitis-B prevention, chemical science, and technology.
  - "Role of Science and Technology in Taiwan,", 1973-1981 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    Includes "The Republic of China and America: Seven Decades of Science and Technology Relations," dated September 1981, by Dr. Bruce Billings.
  - "Science in Taiwan,", 1960-1974 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - "Study of The Role of Science and Technology in Taiwan,", 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "Technology Transfer,", 1972-1976 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - "Transfer of Science and Technology to Taiwan,", 1968-1975 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - "Energy, Economics, and Policies,", 1982 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    Sponsored by the Committee for Scientific and Scholarly (sic) in cooperation with the United States and Academia Sinica, Republic of China.
- Printed matter, 1944-1997
  - Newspaper clippings, 1944-1990 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    Contains news from Taiwanese publications and articles about Bruce Billings. Some clippings include Chinese to English translations.
  - Chinese-American Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction (JCRR): Its organization, policies and objectives, and contributions to the agricultural development of Taiwan, 1970 December (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Newsweek Magazine, 1949 October 17 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    Contains section on foreign affairs highlighting Communist People's Republic Independence Day and Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek's critique on Formosa (Taiwan) and the United States' far east policy.
  - History of Technology in Taiwan in the 1900s, Volume I: Sisal Industry, by Fannie Billings, 1993 July (Box-folder 8: 5)
    Includes photographs and illustrations.
  - History of Technology in Taiwan in the 1900's, Volume II: Straw Rope/Bag, by Bruce H. Billings and Fannie Billings, 1994 July (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - China and the West: Information Technology Transfer from Printing Press to Computer Era, by Bruce Billings, 1997 November (Box-folder 8: 7)
    Includes illustrations.
  - Bruce Hadley Billings mimeograph: A study of the role of science and technology in Taiwan, 1973 July (Text 8: 8)
    Relates to the role of technology in Taiwanese economic development, especially in agriculture.